Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is ל"ט, Lamed Tet,
but we begin at the top of ל"ח עמוד ב, Lamed Chet
Amud Bet, we're a little behind
and the משנה Mishna was about if somebody, again, somebody can't get
הנאה Hana'ah from somebody else: ראובן Reuven can't get הנאה Hana'ah from
שמעון. Shimon. And the משנה Mishna says that nevertheless, שמעון Shimon can
still feed ראובן's Reuven wife and kids. It's a responsibility that
ראובן Reuven has, but it's no different than paying off ראובן's Reuven
creditors. It's seen as not giving direct הנאה Hana'ah to ראובן. Reuven.
And also the question about whether he can feed the animals, that's
actually different because the feeding of the animals is a direct increase
in the value of the net worth of ראובן. Reuven. Now he
has fatter animals and they're worth more. So that actually he's not
allowed to do. And then the discussion about what about non-kosher animals
whose value is not really measured directly in how fat they are
and so on. It's really being that they're, there the idea is
they're being fed in order that they can continue to do work
like the donkey or the horse, etc. Would that be considered directly
giving benefit or not?
So feeding his wife is not beneficial, but feeding his animals is.
Exactly. Now we got it clear.
Fatter. We don't want them to get overweight.
Exactly.
Exactly. Now the גמרא Gemara says, alrighty, calm down everybody. אמר רב
יצחק בר חנניה אמר רב הונא: Amar Rav Yitzchak Bar Chananya Amar
Rav Huna: המודר הנאה מחבירו מותר
להשיאו בתו.
Hamudar hana'ah mechavero mutar lehasilo
bito. Somebody is prevented from, is off limits from somebody else, ראובן
Reuven cannot get benefit from שמעון. Shimon. Well, we'll see if that's
what it means, but that's standardly what it means. He can still,
שמעון Shimon can still marry off to ראובן Reuven his daughter. So
ראובן, Reuven, it sounds like it's saying ראובן Reuven can't get הנאה
Hana'ah from שמעון, Shimon, he can still marry שמעון's Shimon daughter. Alright.
הוי בה רבי זירא. Havi bah Rabbi Zeira. So רבי זירא Rabbi
Zeira asked on this: במאי עסקינן? Bimai askinan? What's the case? אילימא
בנכסי אבי הכלה אסורין על החתן, Ilema b'nichsei avi hakallah asurin al
hachatan, that the father's property is forbidden to the groom, the father
of the bride's property is forbidden to the groom, הרי מוסר לו
שפחה לשמשו. Harey moser lo shifcha leshamsho. Here's a lovely line. So
how could that be? If ראובן Reuven can't get benefit from שמעון,
Shimon, how can he marry שמעון's Shimon daughter? שמעון Shimon is giving
him something. He's giving him a maidservant to serve him. Right? That's
all why we know we got married. See, anybody who has a
problem with gay marriage, it's not about sex, it's about having people
to take care of your needs. So שפחה לשמשו. shifcha leshamsho. I
don't see what everybody is getting up in arms about. Anyway, okay.
This is now on the internet.
Alright. So, because as we learned in כתובות, Kesuvot, a wife has
certain marital obligations to the husband. So marrying off your daughter to
a man, you're actually giving him some object of value. I mean,
it's quite, again,
well, I don't have to comment on it. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says אלא, Ella, so therefore why is that not considered to
be הנאה Hana'ah that he is getting from the bride's father? אלא,
Ella, it must be בנכסי חתן אסורין על אבי הכלה. b'nichsei chatan
asurin al avi hakallah.
So it must be that the case is that actually no, the
groom cannot give benefit to the bride's father. Okay. And then the
חידוש Chiddush is he can marry this man's daughter, and the fact
that he'll then be providing for the food for this man's daughter,
now his wife, is not considered giving benefit to this man. So
the גמרא Gemara says, that's not a big חידוש. Chiddush. You can
even feed his daughter even without having married her. Certainly you'd be
able to feed her once you married her.
So גדולה מזו אמרו. Gedola mizu amru. They said a bigger חידוש.
Chiddush. זן את אשתו ואת בניו, Zan et ishto v'et banav, that
a person can feed
another, if ראובן Reuven can't get benefit from שמעון, Shimon, שמעון Shimon
can still feed ראובן's Reuven wife and children. ואף על פי שהוא
חייב במזונותיהם, V'af al pi shehu chayav bimezonoteihem, even though ראובן Reuven
is obligated to feed his wife and children. שמעון Shimon paying for
their food, giving them food, is not considered directly benefiting ראובן. Reuven.
So if that's true that it's not direct benefit if somebody feeds
my wife and kids even though I have an obligation to them,
so then it goes without saying, ואתה אמרת מותר להשיא את בתו,
v'ata amarta mutar lehasi et bito, it goes without saying that he
could feed the daughter once he's married her. Right? So here, you
get this. Right? Here's...
okay.
Here's ראובן Reuven and here's שמעון. Shimon. Okay?
So ראובן Reuven is not allowed to get הנאה Hana'ah from שמעון.
Shimon. Right? He can't get הנאה Hana'ah from שמעון. Shimon. Okay, but
what can שמעון Shimon do? שמעון Shimon can still feed ראובן's Reuven
kids. I mean also his wife. That's not considered הנאה. Hana'ah. He
can feed the kids because the kids aren't getting direct benefit, because
ראובן Reuven isn't getting direct benefit. Okay, so we said that. Now
you're telling me, ah,
שמעון Shimon can even marry ראובן's Reuven daughter.
Okay, so now he's married to ראובן's Reuven daughter.
Okay. And he can feed her, and he's not giving that's not
considered giving benefit to ראובן. Reuven. Well, of course! If he could
feed the daughter before he married her, when ראובן Reuven was obligated
to feed her, and it's not considered benefit to ראובן, Reuven, then
of course he can marry the daughter and continue to feed her
and it's not considered benefit. That's not a חידוש, chiddush, okay? So
to say that he can marry the daughter and feed her as
his wife, and that's not giving benefit to ראובן Reuven is like
obviously goes without saying. So
what, so we'll say okay, so it's the other way. What it
actually means is, that ראובן Reuven can't give benefit to שמעון, Shimon,
and ראובן Reuven is allowed to marry off his daughter to שמעון.
Shimon. So was that not giving him something of
benefit? Right, even, you're giving him now a wife, and the wife
will attend to his needs. So now ראובן Reuven has given שמעון
Shimon something of benefit. So how is that allowed? So one way
or the other, either it shouldn't be allowed or it's too obvious.
So the גמרא Gemara says, לעולם בשנכסי אבי הכלה אסורין על החתן.
le'olam bishnichsei avi hakallah asurim al hachatan.
So it's like we said. It's that ראובן, Reuven, the father of
the bride, can't give benefit to שמעון, Shimon, okay? And nevertheless, בבתו
בוגרת ומדעתה. be'vito bogeres umida'atah.
The daughter is not his underage daughter. If it's his underage daughter,
then he is the one essentially marrying off the daughter. The daughter
is something of a commodity there, right? I mean the whole idea
of שפחה לשמשו, shifcha leshamesho, the father can sell his daughter as
a servant, as a Hebrew slave, he can marry her off, right?
He is the one that essentially is, she is there for being
basically somewhat commodified and being transferred to another man. That actually would
be a problem. But she's not a minor, and he's not the
one marrying her off. She's an adult. She's a בוגרת. bogeret. She's
all twelve and a half. And she's marrying herself off. So therefore
yes, if ראובן Reuven were to take his underage daughter and give
her to שמעון, Shimon, he'd be giving him something. But if she
is now an adult, right? So she's just here, and she's just
here, he's not giving him anything, she's just marrying herself straight to
שמעון. Shimon. ראובן Reuven isn't giving him anything. ומדעתה. umida'atah. And the
reason it's allowed is because she's doing it on her own. It's
not being married off by her father, she's doing it on her
own. And of course you could still say what's the big חידוש,
chiddush, right? So then it's just somebody related to him. I mean,
ראובן's Reuven cousin can go ahead and marry שמעון, Shimon, so of
course ראובן's Reuven daughter... so it's not such a חידוש. chiddush. So
the ר"ן Ran says maybe the חידוש chiddush is the word ומדעתה,
umida'atah, which means she's the initiator, and not just that he's not
the initiator, but שמעון Shimon is also not the initiator. שמעון Shimon
is not allowed to say to ראובן, Reuven, ראובן, Reuven, I'm interested
in your daughter. Do me a favor, can you try to persuade
her to marry me and to accept my proposal? And if he
were to say that, then that would be that ראובן Reuven would
be giving benefit to שמעון, Shimon, because he would be doing a
service for שמעון. Shimon.
Yes, and two things, A, in that case, that leads us to
the previous סוגיה sugya about שליחות shlichut and זכיה. zachah.
Exactly, exactly.
And number two is, I just want to understand, let's say the
daughter was nine years old. Okay, and so ראובן Reuven marries her
off to שמעון. Shimon. Right. What does that look like? Does that
mean that she goes to שמעון's Shimon house every day and tidies
up and does the... but then lives still with her father, right?
Well, no, because it actually is interesting, you know, it does say
להשיאו את בתו, lehasilo et bito, not לקדשו את בתו. lekadesho et
bito.
קידושין kiddushin would mean she continues to live with her father, she
is just legally married to שמעון. Shimon. So she would live at
home? Right. No, but the שפחה לשמשו shifcha leshamesho taking care of
his needs, the actual living together, the כתובה ketubah obligations, which includes
sex and all of the, well, and all of the domestic responsibilities
is only after נישואין, nisuin, only once they've started living together.
So you're saying... so when that is the verb that's being used...
right, להשיאו את בתו... lehasilo et bito...
right, even if she were nine or ten, that's the implication.
Exactly. Now it is true, again, we've pointed this out before, that
although often there's a discussion about קידושי קטנה, kidushei ketannah,
the what do you call it? The other גמרות Gemaras make it
clear that the נישואין nisuin usually waited until she had become an
adult. Okay, but here it's talking about להשיאו את בתו. lehasilo et
bito. It also raises an important question about what is even if
she's underage, is it the father that's effecting the נישואין? nisuin? The
father effects the קידושין. kiddushin. But since the נישואין nisuin is about
them actually living together, why is the father seen as the one
doing the נישואין? nisuin? Why isn't she the one doing the נישואין?
nisuin? And that might have been a way to address this issue.
But the גמרא, Gemara, so it is definitely interesting that the גמרא
Gemara sees that even the father when she's underage, the father is
even the one who's seen as doing the נישואין, nisuin, not just
her.
And it wouldn't and the חתן chatan wouldn't be doing the נישואין?
nisuin?
Well, yes, but I mean from the bride's side, is the bride
side that she goes walks to the חתן's chatan house and now
she is living with him? So is she being משיאה masi herself
to the חתן, chatan, or is it no that even at that
stage, if she's underage, the father is the one that still hands
her over? Right, if you think about the משנה Mishnah in כתובות
Ketubot about when נישואין nisuin happens and when כתובה ketubah happens, it's
מסרה אבי ה... masra avi ha... The אבי הכלה avi hakalla was
מוסר moser his daughter to the חתן, chassan, right? Does that sound
good, or is something wrong there? Anyway, okay, so anyway, it does
seem certainly in a practical sense if he's a minor that the
father is involved in handing her over and in the נישואין nisuin
itself. Is that okay there?
Something sounds like it's hissing too much. All right, anyway. All right,
well, whatever. We'll find out. Just stay clear of it in case
it blows. All right, so now the גמרא gemara continues.
Okay. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we
taught similarly, המודר הנאה מחברו, hamudar hana'a michaveiro, he cannot marry the
daughter off to this guy. אבל, Aval, if it's an underage daughter
presumably, משיא בתו בוגרת, masi bito bogeres, can marry her off to
him, his adult daughter, ומידעתה, umida'ata, as long as it is she
the one that is essentially doing it. אמר רבי יעקב: Amar Rabbi
Yaakov: המדיר בנו לתלמוד תורה. hamadir beno letalmud torah. Now we have
another fascinating idea and there's two very interesting ways of interpreting this.
Somebody who vows his son, makes a vow about his son regarding
תלמוד תורה. talmud torah. What does that mean? So the ר"ן, Ran,
there are two possible interpretations. The ר"ן Ran says what it means
and he brings a support from a תוספתא, Tosefta, is that somebody
says to his son, I want to so make sure that you
are devoting your time to learning תורה Torah that I am saying
that I, your father, will not get any benefit from you, which
means that in order that you do not waste any time coming
to take care of my needs because you're so good about כיבוד
אב ואם, kibud av va'eim, I am going to say that any
benefit from you is forbidden to me, so therefore you can devote
all of your time to learning תורה. Torah. Okay, so that's what
the ר"ן Ran says, he has evidence from a תוספתא, Tosefta, but
the רש"י Rashi here, not really the רש"י, Rashi, but the מפרש,
mefaresh, says something different, which seems like something that's more consistent with
other phenomenon discussions we have in the גמרא gemara in other places,
which is that the father says to the son, if you do
not devote your time to learning תורה, Torah, then all of my
property is forbidden to you. So it's basically used as a leverage
and a threat in order to get the son to spend his
time learning תורה. Torah. Okay, so sort of like, and so anyway,
one way or the other, but we'll read it the ר"ן's Ran
way, okay? So the father says I won't get any benefit from
you so that you spend all your time learning תורה. Torah. מותר
למלאות לו חבית של מים Mutar lemallos lo chavis shemayim ולהדליק לו
את הנר. ulehadlik lo es haneir. The son can still go ahead,
reading it the ר"ן's Ran way, and fill up his father's, you
know, fill up a barrel of water for the father. I basically,
what this fill up the barrel of the water, I mean there's
pretty I guess it's obvious, but I once actually saw it, I
was in this village in Senegal, you know, where they had to
draw the water from the well, so it's not every time you
need to wash your hands you go to the well. First thing
in the morning is you draw water from a well and you
bring it over and you fill up this huge barrel that's like
in the village or by the house and then you spend the
rest of the day using the barrel, using the water in the
barrel.
Okay, so in point is home delivery.
There you go. Okay, and so it's not a trivial service at
all by the way, למלאות לו חבית של מים, lemallos lo chavis
shemayim, ולהדליק לו את הנר, ulehadlik lo es haneir, and to light
a candle. So somehow it's understood that even though he said, now
this is fascinating, right? Because until now we were being very formalistic.
What's defined as benefit? It has to come direct. Paying off a
creditor isn't benefit, this is, this isn't, but like some very formalistic
way of determining it, you know, here we're basically using context and
we're saying in this particular case of a father and a son
and part of the purpose of the תלמוד תורה talmud torah idea
is that it's not that there is some type of a fight
between them. If there's a fight between them and you say I
won't get any benefit, then you want it to be all off
limits. But here it's a father and a son and it's for
a good purpose, so we're going to use that context to say
that certain things implicitly weren't included, like he wouldn't, you know, to
do something like the, I don't know, the trivial service of lighting
a candle is one thing, I really don't get the filling of
the water of the barrel, but somehow it's understood like obviously that
basic type of a thing that we weren't, we were excluding, maybe
I don't know, maybe that's first thing in the morning and last
thing at night, you know, so we use that context to explain
that certain types of things weren't meant to be included even though
they very clearly are הנאה. hana'a. All right, רב יצחק אמר: Rav
Yitzchak amar: לצלות לו דג קטן, litzlos lo dag katan, not only
that, but even if to fry a little bit of a fish.
So it becomes so funny, so what exactly is off limits if
those things are okay? Where exactly do you draw the line? Right?
So that's why it's so much easier to have formal parameters. So
this is really a fascinating גמרא gemara in shifting gears where if
based on context we might say he never meant to make this
אסור, assur, he never meant to make that אסור, assur, even though
it's certainly included in the words. אמר רבי ירמיה אמר רבי יוחנן:
Amar Rabbi Yirmiya amar Rabbi Yochanan: המודר הנאה מחבירו מותר להשקותו כוס
של שלום. hamudar hana'a mechaveiro mutar lehashkoso kos shel shalom. And now
we have another generic case, not just father and son.
ראובן Reuven says to שמעון, Shimon, I won't get any benefit from
you. שמעון Shimon can still fill up for ראובן Reuven a cup
of greeting, of well wishes or something. מאי ניהו, Mai nihu, what
is this cup of peace? הכא תרגימו, Hacha targimu,
here in בבל Bavel they explained it,
כוס של בית האבל, kos shel beis ha'aveil, that when he is
in... You do ניחום אבלים nichum aveilim and we're going to talk
about things like ביקור חולים bikur cholim and ניחום אבלים nichum aveilim
and is that a form of giving הנאה hana'ah or is that
considered to be a מצוה mitzvah that's being done? So presumably there
he is doing ניחום אבלים nichum aveilim which is permitted and part
of the ניחום אבלים nichum aveilim is you fill up the cup
for the אבל avel and that's allowed. Now by the way the
ר"ן Ran says in this case
it's got to be the אבל'ס avel's own water. The same way
when it's frying the fish for the father or filling up the
barrel of water, it's actually it's actually the father's fish and the
father's water. And that's important. Meaning even if we're going to use
context to explain what type of services are considered or not considered
הנאה, hana'ah, the actual giving of an object of value from one
person to another will always be defined as הנאה. hana'ah. So the
guy cannot give his water to his father, can't give his fish
to his father. If it's the father's water and the father's fish,
do we consider this service to be a הנאה hana'ah that was
made off limits or not, that maybe we'll use context to explain.
And the same here in terms of the בית beit of this
guy, he can't give his water to the אבל avel but to
do the service of filling up the cup of water if that's
seen as somehow customary then that is not seen as a type
of הנאה hana'ah that was ever intended to be off limits. במערבא
אמרי B'ma'arava amri כוס של בית המרחץ, kos shel beit ha-merchatz, it
doesn't even have to be a tragic case of אבל, avel, even
if like after the שוויץ shvitz or something somebody would give you,
fill up a glass of water, you know, in order to just
because you know you're thirsty, you need water after like giving blood
or after other types of things so that would be okay. Now
why not? You could say that's a tremendous הנאה, hana'ah, like I
really need the cup of water. So you know the ר"ן Ran
also throws in the שלום shalom as a way of like דרכי
שלום. darchei shalom. Like it would just be considered to be like
here I am I'm totally שוויצינג shvitzing or whatever what you can't
even give me a cup of water, like it would- and it's
so funny because so often the reason you make a נדר neder
is because you're having a fight and you want- it's reinforcing the
fight and now we're actually allowing certain things for דרכי שלום, darchei
shalom, things that to not do this would be considered just so
profoundly offensive. So again what is quite fascinating is is that even
when somebody say takes a נדר neder and we're still going to
use context and certain things would clearly be included in the words
or in the category we're going to use context in order to
say that certain things remain allowed. So again the way the ר"ן
Ran says it is any giving of any object of value would
always be forbidden, we wouldn't use context, but in terms of various
types of service, you know in the case of the father and
the son, certain services which were assumed to be that they would
want those to continue or in the case here about just two
people, certain services that like would be just basically customary
and assume that nobody would ever want to exclude those, those still
remain allowed. Okay now we get back to the משנה. mishna. ולא
יזון את הבהמה בין טמאה בין טהורה, V'lo yazon et ha-behemah bein
tmeiah bein tehorah, you cannot feed the animals because that's actually giving
direct increase in value to this person. So תניא tanya and it's
you know it's actually giving food again going to that point an
object to the person's property not using it to satisfy a person's
obligation towards wife and kids but basically contributing your food to the
person's estate. תניא יהושע איש עוזא אומר, Tanya Yehoshua Ish Uzza omer,
יהושע Yehoshua from עוזא Uzza says, זן עבדיו ושפחותיו הכנענים, Zan avadav
u'shifchotav ha-kenaanim,
you can feed his male and female servants, slaves really, okay? Because
again not like the animals it's not like they are being
fattened and that they're increasing in value, okay? ולא יזון את בהמתו
בין טמאה בין טהורה, V'lo yazon et behemato bein tmeiah bein tehorah,
but not the animals whether kosher or non-kosher animals. מאי טעמא, Mai
ta'ama, what's the difference? עבדיו ושפחותיו הכנענים למנחרותא עבדין Avadav u'shifchotav ha-kenaanim
lemancharuta avdin
or some of the versions למנכרוסה עבדין, lemancharusa avdin, I'll read it
that way, because your servants you use to like clean the house
you use them to do service to do tasks and therefore having
a fatter servant or you know is not necessarily or you're not
increasing the value of the service. בהמה לפיטומא עבידא Behemah l'fituma avida
and the animal you want to fatten them because- so giving them
food and you know fattening them and adding some weight to them
as- which is seen as the act of giving them food, that's
seen as directly increasing their value. Even a non-kosher animal right you
can the גמרא Gemara says you know eventually it could be made
into dog food or whatever. But the reason we're emphasizing לפיטומא l'fituma
to fatten is because you'd say a non-kosher animal feeding it is
a benefit because then it'll be strong to do its work right
and it won't decrease in value. So the same would be true
about the servants. So you have to- this actually has to make
the line that it's not enough that you give them, you know,
you maintain their health and allow them to continue to do the
work, then it would be true about the slaves as well. It's
the actual food directly increases the value because it fattens them. All
right so the interesting thing here, you know we gave the example
the other day about like if you take my- I can't get
benefit for you, can you take my car in and do it
and like and get the oil changed? Okay? Because so is that
considered giving me benefit? If you wouldn't get the oil changed it
would break down and it would decrease in value but right now
you're doing a type of a service that
is only- that's a maintenance service that makes- that doesn't actually increase
the value, it just prevents a decrease in value. And that seems
to be the case about sort of feeding my slaves, okay, you
haven't increased their value. just prevented them from getting weaker and from,
and from, and from a decrease. Whereas my animals, by by giving
them food, you actually are adding some, you know, some heft to
that, and that's an actual direct benefit. Get a very interesting line
that's being drawn. Okay, now we turn to the next משנה. Mishnah.
המודר הנאה מחברו, Hamudar hana’ah mechaveiro, ונכנס לבקרו. venichnas levakro.
So now it's similar to the discussion we just had before about
paying a שבעה shiva visit. Somebody cannot get, ראובן Reuven can't get
הנאה hana’ah from שמעון, Shimon, שמעון Shimon can go and pay a
ביקור חולים bikur cholim call to ראובן. Reuven. Okay, now that, again,
it's not a physical benefit of giving him food, okay, it's an
emotional benefit, it's a type of which is sort of seen in
this category of service. Now within this category of service, okay, although
again, there's a difference, right, it's not just you did a service
for me, I actually got some emotional benefit from the fact that
you came and visited me, but again, that's probably in this sort
of מצוות לאו ליהנות ניתנו mitzvot lav lehanot nitnu type of a
category, which is, you know, benefit is measured in more physical, financial
type of terms. So the fact here, it's in this category of
doing a service and doing, giving me some emotional benefit. And there,
if it's in the process of doing a מצווה, mitzvah, that's not
considered to be a problem. So,
so therefore, paying a, paying a ביקור חולים bikur cholim call is
okay. I'm doing a מצווה, mitzvah, and the fact that you somehow
are enjoying it and getting something out of it, but fundamentally, it's
not seen like I am benefiting, that, you know, giving you a
direct benefit.
עומד, Omed, now I can stand, אבל לא יושב, aval lo yoshev,
I can't sit. What exactly the difference is not clear. ומרפא רפואת
נפש, Umerapeh refuat hanefesh, if I am a doctor, I can go
ahead and take care of your, you know, I can, I can
take care of your medical
needs. רפואת נפש Refuat hanefesh doesn't just mean that if your life
is at stake, I can take, I can actually go ahead, take
your pulse, you know, write out a prescription, take care of any
types of medical needs I need to, and that's not considered a
benefit, or it's not forbidden. אבל לא רפואת ממון, Aval lo refuat
mamon, I cannot go ahead and do רפואת ממון, refuat mamon, which
let's for now say it means that if I'm a vet, we'll
see what it might mean in the גמרא, Gemara, but let's for
now say it means that if I'm a vet, I can't go
ahead and take care of your animals, because taking care of your
animals, that's just taking care of your property. Okay, but I can
take care of you. So again, it's quite fascinating. So I get
you can't take care of my property, you're giving, you're helping the
value, my, you know, my net worth, that's הנאה. hana’ah. But how
could רפואת, how could being a doctor for me not be considered
הנאה, hana'ah, you know, physically helping my body and so on? So
very fascinating, we'll have to sort of see all this in the
גמרא. Gemara. Yes.
They're tying ביקור חולים bikur cholim into רפואת הנפש. refuat hanefesh. They
don't say רפואת הגוף, refuat haguf, as another, which is other parts
of the...
Yeah. Yeah, I mean, I know, in our, in our מי שברך,
Mi Shebeirach, we say רפואת הנפש ורפואת הגוף, refuat hanefesh v'refuat haguf,
but here רפואת הנפש. refuat hanefesh.
Yeah, but רפואת הנפש refuat hanefesh means, but it's contrasted to רפואת
ממון, refuat mamon, not רפואת הגוף. refuat haguf.
So רפואת הנפש ורפואת הגוף refuat hanefesh v'refuat haguf is a later
liturgy.
רפואת הנפש Refuat hanefesh just means you can take care of my
bodily needs. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. במאי
עסקינן? Bemay askinan? Now we're going to try to figure out the
difference between paying a standing ביקור חולים bikur cholim call and a
sitting ביקור חולים bikur cholim call. So what are we talking about?
אי בשנכסי מבקר אסורין על החולה, Ei beshnichsei mevaker asurin al hacholeh,
that the visitor, שמעון Shimon is coming to pay a visit to
ראובן, Reuven, ראובן Reuven is sick. So if ראובן Reuven can't get
benefit from שמעון, Shimon, okay, the, the,
the ביקור חולים bikur cholim guy, whatever, the מבקר mevaker cannot...
I don't know why. Okay, let's try this again. Okay, ראובן Reuven
can't get benefit from שמעון. Shimon.
He can't get benefit from שמעון. Shimon. ראובן Reuven here is in
the sickbed.
Doesn't matter. It really doesn't matter. It matters which direction is forbidden.
Okay, ראובן Reuven is in his sickbed. Okay. So, if ראובן Reuven
can't and שמעון Shimon is coming to pay the ביקור חולים bikur
cholim call. So if ראובן Reuven can't get benefit from שמעון, Shimon,
אי בשנכסי מבקר אסורין על החולה, ei beshnichsei mevaker asurin al hacholeh,
אפילו יושב נמי. afilu yoshev nami.
So what's the big deal? שמעון Shimon is paying a ביקור חולים
bikur cholim call, he's doing a מצווה, mitzvah, he's not giving ראובן
Reuven any actual object of benefit. What difference? He should be allowed
to pay a ביקור חולים bikur cholim call standing or sitting. אי
בשנכסי חולה אסורין על המבקר, Ei beshnichsei choleh asurin al hamevaker, now
if however
שמעון Shimon can't get benefit from ראובן, Reuven, right? So now he's
going into ראובן's Reuven house. So going into somebody's house, using somebody's
property, it's quite interesting, cutting, like if I cut through your yard,
I'm getting benefit from you. Here the גמרא Gemara assumes even if
I'm not cutting through your yard, even if I'm just going into
your house, and I'm going into your house because I'm, because I'm
actually take, doing something for your sake. Nevertheless, going on your property
is getting benefit from you. I am having the right to go
on your property. So if שמעון Shimon can't get benefit from ראובן,
Reuven, how could he even stand? How is he allowed to even
go into ראובן's Reuven property? ואי בשנכסי חולה אסורין
על המבקר, אפילו עומד נמי לא, Veei beshnichsei choleh asurin al hamevaker,
afilu omed nami lo, he shouldn't even be able to stand, because
he's going into ראובן's Reuven property. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
שמואל לעולם בשנכסי מבקר אסורין על החולה, Amar Shmuel, le’olam beshnichsei mevaker
asurin al hacholeh, which is obviously the פשט peshat in the משנה.
Mishnah. We're talking about that ראובן Reuven cannot get benefit from שמעון.
Shimon. ובמקום שנותנים שכר לישיבה ואין נותנים שכר על עמידה. u-ve-makom she-notnim
s'char l'yeshiva ve-ein notnim s'char al amidah. This
is sort of like the difference between teaching תורה שבעל פה Torah
She-be'al Pe and תורה שבכתב Torah She-bikhtav that people would get paid
for paying a ביקור חולים bikur cholim call, but they'd get paid
if they would actually spend the time to sit down and spend
some time as opposed to just a quick visit and a hello
how are you doing. So we think that the whole idea of
the profession of chaplaincy where people are paid to go around and
to look in onto the sick people is a new profession. Apparently
there they did it but in a way that seems a little
bit less a little funnier that people would come and pay a
ביקור חולים bikur cholim call and then the sick person would actually
pay them for their time. Thank you for coming and spending time
with me,
here's ten bucks. I don't really understand how what that would do
to the dynamics of paying the call or the sense that this
was such a welcome visit, here's some money for your time. Anyway
it works a little better if a third party is paying for
it than the actual חולה choleh himself. Okay but apparently that's what
they're saying at least what occurred. And therefore but not for simple
just dropping in and saying hi to really sit down and spend
time and spend an hour with a person. So maybe you sort
of also think about it like again maybe it is a little
bit more professional. Like maybe the person's doing it not just like
hi I'm your friend how are you, but sits down and spends
some real time like in a pastoral type of a context and
maybe that would be a service that would be paid for. And
that would be the difference between standing and sitting.
Like a doctor?
Yeah maybe it could be. טוב tov she- but that sort of
gets to the end of the משנה. Mishna. So שמעון Shimon comes
in and just stands, he's just doing a מצוה mitzvah and he's
not giving him any monetary benefit. שמעון Shimon might enjoy it, ראובן
Reuven might enjoy it but that's okay and then he leaves. But
to come and sit that would be something that actually normally he
could demand a fee for and if he's not demanding a fee
for then essentially he is giving that fee back to ראובן. Reuven.
It's sort of like the whole idea of teaching תורה שבכתב Torah
She-bikhtav since you're allowed to demand a fee if you're not charging
the fee you're giving benefit to the person. Okay so that's the
reason.
ובמקום שנותנים שכר לישיבה ואין נותנים שכר על עמידה. u-ve-makom she-notnim s'char
l'yeshiva ve-ein notnim s'char al amidah. מאי פסקא? mai piska? What's the
distinction or why do you draw the line between the two?
הא קמשמע לן דאפילו במקום שנותנים שכר. ha kamashma lan de-afilu b'makom
she-notnim s'char. Even in places where they normally would charge a fee
for paying a excuse me הא קמשמע לן דאפילו במקום שנותנים שכר.
ha kamashma lan de-afilu b'makom she-notnim s'char. Even in places where it
would be acceptable to charge a fee for paying a
sick ביקור חולים bikur cholim call, על ישיבה בעי למשקל על עמידה
לא בעי למשקל. al yeshiva ba-ee l'mishkal al amidah lo ba-ee l'mishkal.
It's acceptable to ask for sitting and it's not acceptable to ask
for standing. Standing is the basic מצוה mitzvah you should not be
asking a fee for a מצוה mitzvah like teaching תורה. Torah.
Sitting is already like you're sitting, you're just doing more of the
מצוה mitzvah but that's seen as going beyond the call of duty
and therefore that is something that it would have been acceptable to
have charged for and by not charging for you are giving benefits
to the person.
Wait, it's also נכסי
מבקר nichsei mevaker
has no object really.
Well it is true that a lot of it is true that
largely we've been talking about that I can't get benefit from you
not just from your property. And here the גמרא Gemara in trying
to clarify who's forbidden on whom it emphasizes whose property is forbidden
on whom. But I think that that's just because it makes it
easier to keep things straight. Once you add the word נכסי nichsei
it makes it clear
who is forbidden on whom. If I say ראובן Reuven is forbidden
on שמעון Shimon or שמעון Shimon is forbidden on ראובן Reuven it's
like wait what did you say? Who can't get benefit from whom?
If you just talk about the people then it's not clear who's
the object who's the subject. If I say ראובן's Reuven property is
forbidden on שמעון Shimon then oh I get what you mean, or
שמעון's Shimon property is forbidden on ראובן. Reuven. So דב Dov makes
an excellent point that technically we have not been talking about an
emphasis on the objects and on the property we've been talking about
the person that is
forbidden to derive benefit from the person. But adding the word נכסי
nichsei is particularly added in these cases where the arrow of direction
isn't clear and the word נכסי nichsei very much identifies who's forbidden
and who's not forbidden.
שהרי נהנה בדריסת הרגל? she-harei nehene be-drisat ha-regel? Like he
that like there's a right?
Yeah but I would not limit this to נכסי nichsei because it's
clear before like the whole issue about שפחה לשמשו shifcha l'shamsho and
the other types of services we really are not emphasizing נכסי. nichsei.
נכסי nichsei is just a word that's being introduced to help identify
who's forbidden to get benefit from whom. Okay so the גמרא Gemara
says okay so that's one answer. ובמקום שנותנים שכר לישיבה ואין נותנים
שכר על עמידה. u-ve-makom she-notnim s'char l'yeshiva ve-ein notnim s'char al amidah.
ואי בעית אימא ve-ee ba'it eima if you want I could say
כדרבי שמעון בן יקים ki-de-Rabbi Shimon ben Yakim
meaning the same logic but take it even further. Even say that
even in a place where they don't charge for sitting it would
still be forbidden to sit. Why? Like רבי שמעון בן יקים Rabbi
Shimon ben Yakim says in another context in a few דפים dapim
גזרה שמא ישהה בעמידה gezeira shema yishei b'amidah that sometimes standing would
actually be allowed in a different context this is not about a
ביקור חולים bikur cholim call but we're going to forbid it because
you'll stay too long. הכא נמי גזרה שמא ישהה בישיבה. hacha nami
gezeira shema yishei b'yeshiva. Here too even if sitting would not be
charged. for so technically it would be allowed, it’s going to be
forbidden because if you spend a lot of time sitting then like
presumably that would be something that everybody would charge for. Okay, so
the only real thing the גמרא Gemara has added here is: why
can you not sit? Because that would be something normally that you
would be entitled to charge the fee for and by not charging
the fee you're giving him benefit. And then the גמרא Gemara is
saying is—so that's in a place where they would charge a fee
for sitting. You're not allowed to sit—you're not allowed to sit without
the fee. But then the גמרא Gemara is saying is even in
a place where they wouldn't charge a fee for sitting, maybe you're
not allowed to sit because even though you're not directly giving him
benefit now, we might be concerned that you'll spend too much time
sitting, right, and then actually that would be something that would demand
a fee and therefore by not taking a fee you'd be giving
it to him. Alright, so basically it's all the same answer, right?
Just a variation. The answer is that coming and doing the ביקור
חולים bikur cholim call, you're doing a מצוה, mitzvah, you're doing a
visit, that's not הנאה, hana'ah and the הנאה hana’ah would be that
you're not charging for things that would be conventionally charged for. What
are the things that are conventionally charged for? Either sitting down or
sitting down a long time. Okay, so if it's a place where
sitting down is conventionally charged for, you can’t sit down. If it's
a place where sitting down is not charged for, you could sit
down or maybe even there you can’t sit down because you'll come
to sit down a long time and then again it’ll be something
that would have been charged for. Alright, so that's the answer of
the גמרא. Gemara. Now the גמרא Gemara continues: עולא אמר לעולם בנכסי
חולה אסורין על המבקר. Ulla amar l'olam b'nechsei choleh asurin al hamivaker.
No,
we'll go back to the other way, that
the—here Reuven's property is forbidden on Shimon. So how can Shimon walk
into Reuven's house? Isn't he getting the benefit of being able to
walk on this person's property? וכגון דלא אדרי מן חיותיה. uk'gon d'lo
adrei min chiyutei. So
and it’s like or what the רן Ran says what this means
is we should assume this sort of goes back to the idea
of like the father and the son and the guy that's giving
a person a, you know, a cup of water after the bath,
that some things were assumed to not be included. So even though
Reuven says I won't get any הנאה hana’ah from you Shimon, it
did not mean to include things that were like central to Reuven's
wellbeing. Okay, so even though it says I won't get any הנאה
hana'ah from you, it doesn't mean that if I'm like drowning in
the ocean I don't want you to throw me a life preserver.
It doesn't mean that if I'm sick I don't want you to
just come and visit me. Okay, that's—things would obviously not have been
included even if I'm in a pique and I'm upset at you
and annoyed at you and whatever, I don't mean some basic things.
It's sort of very similar to the discussion before about this כוס
של שלום. kos shel shalom. There's some basic, you know, human interaction
things that I would not have put off limits. Alright, so that's
why he says that that would be allowed.
Did I—Rabbi שמעון בן אליקים? Shimon ben Elyakim?
No, I read it. Yes, did I? I read it again.
כדרב שמעון בן אליקים גזירה שמא ישהה בעמידה הכא נמי גזירה שמא
ישהה בישיבה.
k'd'Reb Shimon ben Elyakim gezeira
shema yisha'eh b'amidah hacha nami gezeira shema yisha'eh b'yeshivah. Okay. עולא אמר
לעולם בנכסי חולה אסורין על המבקר וכגון דלא אדרי מן חיותיה. Ulla
amar l'olam b'nechsei choleh asurin al hamivaker uk'gon d'lo adrei min chiyutei.
But even so, even though Reuven says, even though Reuven basically says
to Shimon, I don't want you to get any benefit from my
property, so therefore don't walk into my house, it's not when it
is central to Reuven's wellbeing. Okay. אי
הכי ei hachi says the גמרא Gemara אפילו יושב נמי? afilu yoshev
nami? So then
he should be even allowed to sit? says no, הא אפשר בעמידה.
ha efshar b'amidah.
That's not like essential, you know, that's spending too much time and
that would not be like excluded. Alright, so basically what we're saying
is Reuven says to Shimon: You Shimon are not to get any
benefit from me. Now what's central here as the רן Ran points
out, before somebody asked who took the vow and I said did
it matter, here the רן Ran points out that it does matter.
Because Reuven is saying to Shimon: You Shimon can't get any הנאה
hana'ah from my—from me or from my property. But of course Reuven
did not want to exclude basic sort of things that are essential
to Reuven's wellbeing. So it's—of course for Shimon to walk into my
house and pay a visit to me while I'm sick I wouldn't
want to make that off limits. To come and sit and spend
time, that's not essential. Okay, a simple hello, a visit, how are
you, goodbye, I'm leaving, like that little cup of water after I
take my שויץ, shvitz, that is something that I would not have
wanted to be off limits. But to come and spend time, that's
not essential, that remains forbidden. Now that’s only if Reuven took the
vow, because if Reuven took the vow he doesn't want to include
things that are going to—that are important, you know, for Reuven's wellbeing.
If Shimon took the vow not to get benefit from Reuven's property,
right,
then—then he wouldn't be able to even walk in and pay the
visit to Reuven, but if Reuven is saying I don't want you
to get benefit from me, of course if I really do want
you to come—if it's something I really need then I want you
to come and take care of me and come and visit me
and see how I'm doing. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara continues:
מיתיבי, meisvei, I'll ask you on this: חלה
הוא נכנס לבקרו,
cholah hu
nichnas l'vakro, if—if he gets sick, the other guy can come and
visit him. חלה בנו שואלו בשוק, chala b'no sho'alo b'shuk, if his
son however gets
sick, you can't go visit the son but you can ask the
guy in the marketplace how's your... How's your son doing? That's not
considered a הנאה hana'ah. asking after somebody's well-being. Again it's quite fascinating.
These are things that are so good for our you know sort
of emotional and social well-being and they're not considered a הנאה. hana'ah.
So the גמרא Gemara says, בשלמא לעולא bishlema le'ula דאמר בשנכסי חולה
אסורין על המבקר d'amar b'sinechsei choleh asurin al hamevaker that that
that
that ראובן's Reuven's property is forbidden on שמעון Shimon and the only
reason שמעון Shimon can go in is because it's essential to ראובן's
Reuven's well-being and that wasn't included, then we understand the difference between
him and son. וחזוני דלא אדרי מין חיותיה v'chizonei delo adri min
chiyusei but he did not want to make off limits things that
were essential to his well-being, so שפיר shapir makes sense, right? So
why is it that שמעון Shimon can go and pay a ביקור
חולים bikur cholim call to ראובן Reuven but not ראובן's Reuven's son?
So the way עולא Ula says it, it makes sense, because ראובן
Reuven says, I don't want you to get any benefit from my
property. Okay, I don't want you walking in my house getting any
benefit from my property. Of course, but he didn't want to exclude
things that were essential to his own well-being. So שמעון Shimon can
go in and say hi, how you doing? ראובן Reuven wouldn't have
wanted to exclude that. He can't sit and spend time, that's not
necessary. He can't come in and visit ראובן's Reuven's son, because that's
not directly essential to ראובן's Reuven's well-being. So there it makes sense
why he's allowed to come in to visit ראובן, Reuven, but he
can't sit and he can't visit ראובן's Reuven's ראובן's Reuven's son, because
fundamentally all the property is off-limits and the only thing that's allowed
are things that are essential to ראובן's Reuven's well-being. That makes sense.
אלא לשמואל ella l'shmuel דאמר בשנכסי מבקר אסורין על החולה d'amar b'sinechsei
mevaker asurin al hacholeh but according to שמואל Shmuel that says it's
the opposite. ראובן Reuven can't get benefit from שמעון. Shimon. Okay? And
what's the benefit? The benefit is what you would charge for, right?
That if you would charge for something and you're not charging, that's
the benefit. So if that's true, אסורין על החולה asurin al hacholeh
מאי שנא הוא מאי שנא בנו? mai shena hu mai shena beno?
What's the difference between him and his son? Actually, as the ר"ן
Ran points out, it would be more מותר mutar to visit the
son. The same way I can feed your son, right? I should
be able to visit your son. The only problem here is when
I'm doing you a service and I'm not asking you to pay
for me, it's like I'm giving you the money of the service.
So if that's true, I can certainly go ahead and visit your
son, that's not anything you would owe me, that's nothing I'm giving
you directly. So how is it that the ברייתא braita does not
allow me to visit the guy's son? So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר לך מתניתין amar lach matnitin you're right. There's no in
you're totally right in terms of the ברייתא. braita. אמר לך מתניתין
amar lach matnitin בשנכסי מבקר אסורין על החולה. b'sinechsei mevaker asurin al
hacholeh. The what I said which was explaining the משנה. Mishnah. The
משנה Mishnah is is when ראובן Reuven can't get any benefit from
שמעון. Shimon. And the issue is sitting versus standing is an issue
about whether you would charge for it or not charge for it.
That's the משנה. Mishnah. But ברייתא braita אסורין על החולה... asurin al
hacholeh... ברייתא braita the ברייתא braita which distinguishes between him and the
son, that's like עולא Ula said: בשנכסי חולה אסורין על המבקר. b'sinechsei
choleh asurin al hamevaker. It's the when the it's the opposite direction.
It's that when it's when the ראובן Reuven when שמעון Shimon can't...
okay. שמעון Shimon can't get any הנאה.
hana'ah So the
משנה Mishnah is when ראובן Reuven can't get any הנאה hana'ah. from
שמעון. Shimon. Okay, that's the משנה. Mishnah. And therefore he can't do
and therefore the sitting is something that he would charge for and
that would be considered הנאה. hana'ah And as far as the משנה
Mishnah is concerned, he can visit the son. Okay? He can visit
the he can visit the son because that's not giving any הנאה
hana'ah, to ראובן, Reuven, that's okay. Okay, but to visit ראובן Reuven
and not charge for it, that's no good. That's the משנה. Mishnah.
The ברייתא braita is the opposite. The ברייתא braita he says I
concede עולא's Ula read as far as the ברייתא braita is concerned.
The ברייתא braita is when שמעון Shimon can't get benefit from ראובן.
Reuven. He can go in to pay a call even though he's
going on the property because that is something essential to ראובן's Reuven's
well-being and ראובן Reuven would not have wanted to make that forbidden,
but he cannot go onto the property and visit the son because
that's not essential to ראובן's Reuven's well-being and therefore he's not allowed
to go onto the property for that purpose.
In this scenario wait, let me just read it.
ברייתא בשנכסי חולה אסורין על המבקר. braita b'sinechsei choleh asurin al hamevaker.
מאי פסקא mai piska so what makes you distinguish? Why read the
משנה Mishnah one way and the ברייתא braita the other way? We
understand why you had to read the ברייתא braita like עולא. Ula.
The ברייתא braita proves עולא's Ula point because it makes the son
off-limits. So once you're reading the ברייתא braita this way, read the
משנה Mishnah this way. Let's have a consistent read and it's all
let עולא Ula be right even as far as the משנה Mishnah
is concerned. So אמר רבא אמר שמואל amar Rava amar Shmuel or
שמואל... Shmuel... excuse me... מתניתין קשיא ליה. matnitin kashya lei. No, שמואל
Shmuel was bothered with the language of the משנה. Mishnah. מאי איריא
דתני עומד אבל לא יושב? mai irya d'tani omed aval lo yoshev?
שמע מינה shma mina דנכסי מבקר אסורין על החולה. d'nechsei mevaker asurin
al hacholeh. The only way he said that שמעון Shimon could explain
the difference between standing and sitting is when ראובן Reuven can't get
benefit from שמעון. Shimon. ראובן Reuven can't get benefit from שמעון, Shimon,
I understand the difference of standing versus sitting. Standing is considered not
benefit, it wouldn't be charged for. Sitting is benefit, it would be
charged for. So that difference of standing and sitting only makes is
an issue in this direction. Why? Because he is saying if it
is this way and שמעון Shimon is allowed to come in because
that's essential for ראובן's Reuven well-being and that's considered to be not
included in the נדר, neder, then logically, if he can walk in
and pay a visit, he can also come and sit in and
pay a visit. If that was the scene to be I would
not have wanted to exclude certain things which are essential for my
well-being, I probably wouldn't have distinguished between standing versus sitting.
Okay, in that scenario, the scenario though
ראובן Reuven cannot- he can't waive the שכר, shchar, right? He can't
waive it.
Well, that's exactly the point. Well, that yeah, exactly. Because now, so
bottom line is what? If ראובן Reuven is the one who takes
the vow then and says you can't get any benefit from me,
similar to the whole idea about drinking the cup of water and
about the father and the son, that would not include certain services
that would be essential to ראובן's Reuven well-being, which would be if
ראובן Reuven is sick, of course I would then want you to
be able to come onto my property to pay me a ביקור
חולים bikur cholim call, maybe according to שמואל Shmuel even to sit
down and pay me a ביקור חולים bikur cholim call and spend
some time with me. Okay, so that's again an interesting case where
certain services are seen as not included in the נדר neder based
on context and what we assume people want. Okay, if however it's
the opposite direction, we get back to the idea like teaching תורה,
Torah, that doing a service that's a מצוה mitzvah is not הנאה,
hana'ah, but if it's something that normally would be charged for, like
sitting down for a long ביקור חולים bikur cholim call seems like
it would be charged for, that would be הנאה, hana'ah that would
be something that could be charged- that to not take the money
would be to give the person הנאה and that would be a
problem. All right, now the גמרא Gemara switches gears and we get
into a nice little אגדתא, aggadeta, yes.
Is this a unique
case
by פסקא pasqa or is it throughout ש"ס? Shas?
No, it's a regular thing, no, it's a phrase, מה פסקא mah
piska like what made you distinguish between-
yeah, or what's the-
no, it's more like what's the basis for distinction? It's normally used
for like why do we assume that this always is this way
and this always is this way, like if you're distinguishing between two
cases, like what makes you distinguish between them? Why are we assuming
they're different? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay. אמר
ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, now we get to a slightly different
tack, which is interesting. It's so fun since the, you know, משנה
Mishnah talks about teaching תורה, Torah, let us discuss the issue about
teaching תורה שבכתב Torah she-bi-khtav and שבעל פה, she-be'al peh, charging for
it. Then we talk about ביקור חולים, bikur cholim, so of course
we find out a fascinating fact that they would charge for ביקור
חולים bikur cholim calls at least for some of them. Now we
get to talk about ביקור חולים. bikur cholim. So let's take a
look. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, רמז לביקור חולים מן התורה
מנין? remez l'bikur cholim min ha-Torah minayin? Where do you get this
hint to the idea of ביקור חולים? bikur cholim? It's quite interesting
about ביקור חולים, bikur cholim, you know, רמב"ם Rambam already says that
ביקור חולים bikur cholim is a קיום kiyum in the מצוה דאורייתא
mitzvah de-oraita ואהבת לרעך כמוך, v'ahavta l're'acha kamocha, right? It's very basic,
right? It's like, you know, you know, you want when you get
sick people to visit you and, you know, and they want when
they get, you know, to be visited. It's one of those basic
sort of things that we want in a society for people to
do for one another and it's part of that מצוה mitzvah ואהבת
לרעך כמוך. v'ahavta l're'acha kamocha. Nevertheless, the דרבנן, de-rabbanan, this is the
way רמב"ם Rambam expresses it, the rabbinic concretization and expression of this
generic מצוה דאורייתא mitzvah de-oraita ואהבת לרעך כמוך v'ahavta l're'acha kamocha is
in things like ביקור חולים, bikur cholim, ניחום אבלים, nichum aveilim, הכנסת
כלה, hachnasas kallah, they identifying- הכנסת אורחים, hachnasas orchim, you know, identifying
very concrete and specific expressions of it. And by the way, there's
a real power, right? Because if something is all-encompassing and generic, it's
like if God is everywhere then God is nowhere, right? There's a
reason for a בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and a בית הכנסת Beit
Knesset or whatever, because otherwise if it's like everywhere then there's nothing
that actually puts any, you know, meat on it, you know, any
meat and bones on it and makes it very specific and concrete.
So nobody- very few people feel obligated by a generic ואהבת לרעך
כמוך, v'ahavta l're'acha kamocha, but something like, oh, there's a מצוה mitzvah
of ביקור חולים, bikur cholim, there's a מצוה mitzvah of ניחום אבלים,
nichum aveilim, right, of הכנסת אורחים, hachnasas orchim, that's something concrete that
we can relate to. So it's a fascinating thing that it's, you
know, רמב"ם Rambam says it's part of a מצוה דאורייתא, mitzvah de-oraita,
but it's also been given very concrete rabbinic expression. And now the
גמרא Gemara wants to see like where do we see specifically this
type of an idea of, you know, this concept. So- That's like
תפילה, tefillah,
that there's a generic עבודה שבלב avodah she-be-lev and then the rabbis
make it concrete with language, say these words.
That's true, although it's a little different because there it's- yeah, it's-
yes, I mean there's a very distinct character of these different types
of ואהבת לרעך כמוך. v'ahavta l're'acha kamocha. Okay, so anyway, אמר ריש
לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, רמז לביקור חולים מן התורה מנין? remez l'bikur
cholim min ha-Torah minayin? Where do you get this idea? שנאמר אם
כמות כל האדם ימותון
אלה, shene'emar im kemot kol ha-adam yemutun eleh, see, recently the פרשה
parsha here, if- if these people by קרח Korach die like normal
people die,
ופקודת כל אדם יפקד עליהם u-fkudat kol ha-adam yipaked aleihem then לא
ה' שלחני. lo Hashem shelachani. So מה משמע? mah mashma?
Where do you get that from that פסוק? pasuk? אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, here's what משה Moshe was saying. אם כמות כל האדם ימותון
אלה im kemot kol ha-adam yemutun eleh if these people die like
normal people die, how do normal people die? שהן חולין, she-hein cholin,
that they're sick, ומוטלין בערסתן u-mutalin b'arsatan and they're lying in their
sickbed, ובני אדם מבקרין אותם u-vnei adam mevakrin otam
and people come in. and visit them and see how they're doing.
So מה בריות אומרים mah briyos omrim that if that would be
how these people die after a long old age and lying sick
and people coming and visiting and seeing how they're doing, then people
say לא השם שלחני לזה lo Hashem shelachani lezeh that God did
not send me on this, that I was not appointed by God.
Anyway, where do you get this from the פסוק? pasuk? Because ופקדת
כל אדם, ufkudat kol adam, לפקד lifpaked can mean, like, to visit.
So it's like, so if these people die like all normal people
die with people coming and visiting them as they are dying and
lying sick, then לא השם שלחני. lo Hashem shelachani. So פקדת כל
אדם pkudat kol adam is seen as referring to the visiting that
is done when a person is lying sick. דרש רבא, Darash Rava,
now רבא Rava explicated: אם בריאה, im briah, since we're talking about
קרח, Korach, אם בריאה יברא השם, im briah yivrah Hashem, if God
will create a creation and the land will open up its mouth,
right, you know, then that will prove that God has sent me.
So what does it mean אם בריאה יברא השם? im briah yivrah
Hashem? So reading it as אם בריאה, im briah, if it's already
been created, good, and if not, יברא השם, yivrah Hashem, let God
create it. אם בריאה גיהנום, im briah Gehennom, if גיהנום Gehennom has
already been created, because that's understood with like the land is going
to open up and bring them to גיהנום, Gehennom, מוטב, mutav, then
great, then תהיה, tiyeh,
let it be like that. אם לאו, im lav, but if it
hasn't already been created, then יברא השם, yivrah Hashem, let God create
גיהנום Gehennom in order to swallow them up. איני, eini, is this
really true that גיהנום Gehennom might not have been created yet? והתניא,
ve'hatanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, שבעה דברים נבראו קודם שנברא
העולם, shiva devarim nivre'u kodem shenivra ha'olam, seven things were created before
the world was created. The ר"ן Ran says it doesn't literally mean
created, because if the world hasn't been created, how were they created?
But anyway, it means they were already part of the plan. What
were they? תורה ותשובה, Torah u'teshuva, תורה Torah and repentance, גן עדן
וגיהנום, Gan Eden ve'Gehennom, גן עדן Gan Eden and גיהנום, Gehennom, כסא
הכבוד ובית המקדש ושמו של משיח, kisei hakavod u'veit hamikdash u'shmo shel
mashiach, the divine throne, the temple, and the name of משיח. mashiach.
So obviously there's
a theological statement about what the world is about,
or what's necessary in terms of a sense of human agency and
religious meaning
in the world. תורה דכתיב השם קנני ראשית דרכו, Torah dechtiv Hashem
kanani reishit darko, God acquired me the first of his paths. תשובה
דכתיב בטרם הרים ילדו ותחולל, teshuva dechtiv beterem harim yuladu u'secholel, before
the mountains were given birth to, תשב אנוש עד דכא, tashev enosh
ad daka, person would return until being trampled down, so that's before
the very mountains were created, there was this sense of תשובה, teshuva,
sort of an acknowledgment of human fallibility and the possibility of getting
up and תיקון tikkun and return, and that that, so it's a
very powerful statement that the idea of free choice but also the
ability to correct one's errors and to always reinvent oneself was always
there and necessary for religious well-being.
Okay, תשב אנוש עד דכא, tashev enosh ad daka, where were we?
גן עדן דכתיב, Gan Eden dechtiv, and then of course part of
that is the sense about reward and punishment. So גן עדן Gan
Eden as it says ויטע השם אלקים גן בעדן מקדם, vayita Hashem
Elokim gan be'eden mikedem, I assume this means not just the גן
עדן Gan Eden of אדם וחוה Adam ve'Chava but eventually a sense
of reward and punishment the opposite of גיהנום. Gehennom. So God did
it מקדם, mikedem, originally. גיהנום דכתיב כי ערוך מאתמול תפתה, Gehennom dechtiv
ki aruch me'etmol tafteh, because it's laid out from yesterday, it will
seduce you. So yesterday from even beforehand, so the sense of free
choice and the things that are seducing you to do good and
inspiring you to do good, seducing you to do evil, the consequences
of it, the תורה Torah which is showing you the right path,
the תשובה teshuva which is showing you how to return if you
ever stumble, all of that was already part of the whole system.
כסא הכבוד דכתיב נכון כסאך מאז, kisei hakavod dechtiv nachon kiseicha mei'az,
so God's divine throne. So what exactly that means
in terms of presumably a throne suggests the idea of being a
king, right? So the fact that God's ultimately God's relationship with human
beings, and I see the כסא הכבוד kisei hakavod as some physical
expression of giving us a way of relating to God or God's
sovereignty over us, right?
So and
בית המקדש דכתיב כסא כבוד מרום מראשון. beit hamikdash dechtiv kisei kavod
marom me'rishon.
So I'm not exactly sure how that's specifically the בית המקדש beit
hamikdash as opposed to just the כסא הכבוד, kisei hakavod, but again,
that is God's sovereignty as expressed on earth. So God's sovereignty up
in heaven and then God's sovereignty as expressed in earth, so creating
that channel of connection of us to God. And ושמו של משיח,
u'shmo shel mashiach, ultimately the fact that the world will be redeemed,
that history has a direction and that we are working towards a
redeemed world. דכתיב יהי שמו לעולם, dechtiv yehi shemo l'olam, and לעולם
l'olam meaning forever even beforehand. Anyway, so that was an extremely powerful
theological statement and all that shows that גיהנום Gehennom was already around.
So what does משה Moshe mean if it doesn't exist that God
create it? אלא ella הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is what משה
Moshe said: אי אברי ליה פומא i ivrei lei puma מוטב, mutav,
if the mouth to גיהנום Gehenom has already been created, good. ואם
לאו, v'im lav, and if it hasn't been created, יברא השם, yivra
Hashem, let God open up that mouth right here and swallow these
people up. So גמרא Gemara says, הכתיב, hachtiv, אין כל חדש תחת
השמש. ein kol chadash tachat hashemesh. How could it be that the
mouth to גיהנום Gehenom hadn't been created? It says there's nothing new
under the sun, so nothing really fundamentally new could be created, and
some very interesting questions about all the other נסים nissim in the
תורה. Torah. הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, here's what he means: אי הכא
לא מקרא פומא, i hacha lo mikra puma, if the mouth isn't
near here, the mouth to גיהנום, Gehenom, להכא ליקרי, lehacha likrei, let
it let it move to here. So we're not creating the mouth
to גיהנום Gehenom new, but let it sort of relocate here, that's
not totally new.
Alright, fascinating question in the whole sense about how dealing with the
idea of נסים nissim in the תורה Torah and so on. Let's
just read one more thing. דרש רבא אמרו ליה רב יצחק: darash
Rava amru lei Rav Yitzchak: מאי דכתיב, mai d'chtiv, what is meant
by the verse, שמש ירח עמד זבולה, shemesh yarei'ach amad zvula, the
sun, the moon stood זבולה zvula in God in the dwelling place
or in the- so what does that mean? שמש וירח בזבול מאי
בעיון? shemesh v'yarei'ach bi'Zvul mai ba'ayon? What did the sun and the
moon are they doing in the זבול? Zvul? The זבול Zvul was
seen as like one of the heavens, זבול Zvul means like a
dwelling place, a domicile, but it's understood to be also one of
the heavens that is closer to God and further from the earth.
The רקיע Rakia is the heaven that is sort of that we
that we know of, that we see, the sky. So what are
they doing up in the זבול? Zvul? They belong in the רקיע!
Rakia! והא ברקיע קביעי? v'ha barakia kvii? They're fixed in the רקיע.
Rakia. What are they doing way up there in the זבול? Zvul?
So מלמד שעלו שמש וירח מרקיע לזבול, melamed she'alu shemesh v'yarei'ach merakia
l'Zvul, they went up from the רקיע Rakia to the זבול, Zvul,
ואמרו לפניו, v'amru lifanav, and said to God: ריבונו של עולם, Ribono
Shel Olam, master of the universe, אם אתה עושה דין לבן עמרם,
im ata oseh din l'ven Amram, because this פסוק pasuk is being
read, the רמב"ן Ramban points out if you look at the context,
it speaks about the יציאת מצרים Yetzias Mitzrayim and the wicked being
punished. So חז"ל Chazal are understanding that the context of this פסוק
pasuk is when משה Moshe was dealing with קרח Korach and those
were the wicked that were being punished, and that's the context of
this פסוק. pasuk. So here it is משה Moshe is having his
fight with קרח, Korach, and the sun and the moon go up
to God and say, master of the universe, if you do not
come to defend the honor of the son of עמרם, Amram, if
you do defend the honor, אנו מאירין, anu me'irin, we will give
light to the world. ואם לאו, v'im lav, and if you don't
defend משה's Moshe honor, אין אנו מאירין, ein anu me'irin, we will
not give light to the world.
באותה שעה, b'osah sha'ah, that moment, ירה בהן חצים וחניתות. yara bahen
chitzim v'chanitos. God threw into the sun and the moon arrows and
spears. אמר להם, amar lahem, and said to them, get back to
your job! בכל יום ויום, b'chol yom v'yom, every day, משתחוים לכם,
mishtachavim lachem, the pagans bow down to you, ואתם מאירין, v'atem me'irin,
and you're happy to give light to the world. בכבודי לא מחיתם,
b'chvodi lo m'chisem, for my honor you did not object. בכבוד בשר
ודם מחיתם? b'chvod basar v'dam m'chisem? You're only going on strike for
משה's Moshe honor? Okay, so therefore get back to work! ובכל יום
ויום יורה בהן חצים וחניתות, u'vchol yom v'yom yoreh bahen chitzim v'chanitos,
and now because of this, from that day forward, God every single
day throws arrows and spears at the sun and the moon to
get them to do their job,
ומאירין, u'me'irin, and only then they give light, שנאמר, shene'emar, לאור חציך
יהלכו, l'or chitzecha yeilechu, for the light of your arrows they will
go. So they move in the heavens and they rotate around the
earth or whatever and they give light because God is shooting arrows
at them. Okay, we will end here for now and we will
continue on ביקור חולים Bikur Cholim tomorrow.
Not influenced in any way by other cultures and their mythologies.
Exactly.